Well, what what has changed or what is
different? What has not changed [music]
is the lack of emphasis on the data
itself. There is still a lot of emphasis
on technology. [music] I have found and
I'm going to exaggerate this just a
little bit to make a [music] point but I
have seen that organizations will spend
millions tens of [music] millions of
dollars on technology and yet they're
not willing to spend hundreds of
thousands of dollars on the data that
powers [music] the technology the data
which is the reason that the technology
[music] exists. So that is something
that is still a challenge.
Welcome to the signal room where
leadership, ethics, and innovation meet
at the intersection of healthcare, data,
and AI. I'm Chris Hutchkins, and here we
cut through the noise to uncover the
signals that matter, the choices, the
challenges, and the conversations
shaping how technology serves people.
Our topic today is garbage in Gen AI
out. The rising cost of ignoring data
quality in the age of AI. Before AI
became the default strategy, before data
was seen as a currency, Danette McGilvray
was already doing the work of making
information usable, trusted, and fit for
purpose. Today on the Signal Room, we're
joined by Danette, the president of
Granite Falls Consulting, which is
celebrating its 20th anniversary. Happy
anniversary, by the way. and with more
than five global high-tech firms and
over two decades in data leadership in
the heart of Silicon Valley. She's
helped Fortune 500 companies, federal
agencies, public institutions, all build
trust in their data before any building
anything else. So in this episode, we
ask what happens when generative AI is
deployed without quality guard rails and
why poor data isn't just a technical
issue but a a strategic ethical one. So
from hidden costs to real world harm
then that brings clarity, urgency and a
blueprint for action.
And as we get started, I just want to
frame the conversation for us. The race
to scale AI is outpacing organizations
ability to ensure the data behind it is
fit for use. Dan, welcome to the sign
room first of all.
Thank you, Chris. Really happy to be
here. Well, I'm I'm excited to be having
the conversation with you today. It was
a pleasant surprise that we ran into
each other at the put data first con uh
conference in uh Las Vegas a couple
weeks back.
Yes. Always nice to meet in person.
Yeah. So, I think we had a lot of uh
very interesting conversations. I know I
learned a ton. you know the one round
table that I got to to sit with you I
was really taken by the depth of
understanding that you bring across
multiple ind industries not only the
ones that are that I'm worried about
most like in the healthcare space but I
think what was really powerful is
understanding that there's there's
ethical concerns when it comes to data
quality it's not just having bad data um
that you know it's just a technical
problem or uh incomplete or whatever
there's ethical reasons behind why it's
such an important thing and why you've
committed your career to really
addressing data quality. So, as we get
started, you know, with with over 30
years working in data quality, long
before most most companies had chief
data officers, which is still a new
thing, what's changed most about the way
leaders value or ignore data
in its quality today?
Oh, well, what what has changed or what
is different? I would say um what has
not changed is the lack of emphasis on
the data itself.
There is still a lot of emphasis on
technology. I am all for technology. So
some of the tools that we use now even
within the data quality space not
counting the tools that organizations
use to do their businesses better. I
love them. I'm very happy for them. But
I have found and I'm going to exaggerate
this just a little bit to make a point.
But I have seen that organizations will
spend millions, tens of millions of
dollars on technology. And yet they're
not willing to spend hundreds of
thousands of dollars on the data that
powers the technology. The data which is
the reason that the technology exists.
So that is something that is still a
challenge for um anyone who cares about
the data and really wants this
technology to reach its full potential.
So what you're describing is not just a
technical problem, it's a leadership
issue.
It Yeah, it is. It is absolutely a
leadership issue and I think you really
said it well in this introduction when
you were talking about the race to AI.
You know, very important. Um, everyone
wants to be first
and I I'm going to use this example of
something that was really disappointing
to me. So when chat GPT first came out,
I feel like it should have had a warning
flag and big flashing red lights on the
front page saying right
this can give you wrong answers.
This is not fully um tested, shall we
say? Now I did find that information
but it took some clicks
and very fine print to find it. It's
interesting that now I can see
um much more clearly that chat GPT and I
looked at this just a month or so ago.
Chat GPT now says
chat GPT is not meant to give advice.
Some of the answers may be wrong.
Are you kidding me?
Right. [laughter]
It's a little It's a little late for
that.
It is. especially for the general
population who has heard about this is
caused a lot of excitement
um not not really knowing that they need
to be more cautious.
is giving them that's a great point
because you know people get comfortable
with technology rather quickly these
days and it's kind of sad I think and I
when I talked to you earlier I'd
mentioned a conversation about trust
that I had had recently with a
psychologist and we've been thinking
about trusting AI but we have a bigger
problem and that people don't trust
people like they used to so what's
really frightening is there's people who
are trusting this capability and they're
not likely even listening to to the
instruction around, you know, what they
should or shouldn't use it for. This is
this is a real problem.
Yes. And this would this is going to go
back to the leadership piece that you
were just talking about. So when ch uh
AI comes forward, companies uh we heard
stories about people who were putting
questions to chat GPT and in the process
of that were giving away proprietary
information because people were not
aware of how it was going to be used,
who else could access it,
um you know what things were made
available
when these new technologies 's come out.
It is up to leadership to say, can we
use this?
Right?
Should we use this? If we should, how
can we be smart about it? How can we
protect ourselves? And I think the race,
too many of the basic questions were not
asked and answered,
right? Yeah. It's it's interesting when
you think about the the natural behavior
of the platform. It's
it's it's in and of itself proving that
it shouldn't be trusted. Um I think we
talked about this when we were in Las
Vegas together recently is that whatever
you tell it, it seems to acknowledge it,
but if you tell it not to do something,
the next thing it does almost always is
exactly what you told it not to. So,
it's not even safe to trust it after you
tell it what you need it to do. It's
just like a a a child.
It
Well, and it's interesting, and I think
you and I might have talked about this
um a little bit before, which was it's
almost too human in that it's trying to
please you. So for instance, we have
documented incidences
of of AI making up references like
check the references. You look at the
reference.
It looks good. It's formatted. It's in
the the same format. Looks real. It's a
madeup reference. So
right
it's really important for people take
the good that they can get from that but
I would say you need to verify you need
to check.
Yes.
So the same thing would be true. So when
you go out to Google and you look for
something it comes up with an AI
overview.
So you're seeing an AI overview
before you see the source data. You need
to scroll down. I I have had things
where the overview of things that I know
and the things that I do h looks pretty
good. It's maybe it's 90% right,
but there were things that were wrong.
So the thing I worry about is when
experts like you and I are gone, how are
people going to be able to tell the
difference? So I think it is really up
to everyone who uses AI. Go to the
sources,
do some testing, do do much testing,
right?
Um but but we we really need to take it
upon ourselves to to not individually
just take the easy way out.
Oh yeah, there's the overview. Let me
just take that. It might be right. Is
it?
Now, this is a really important point
because if we don't catch those things,
we're also training the model, which
means we're further embedding that
information that other people can be
tripped up and and used inappropriately.
So, this I don't know if we could even
overstate the importance of this. I I
just think it's really really critical
that people understand.
Yeah, absolutely. And when you when you
talk about the training, so the training
of these models are coming from data
that is out in the world. Yes.
Right.
We know that bias I'm going to talk
about bias for a minute.
We know bias is out in the world,
right?
And there was a an article that came out
in Computer World in July about some
some research that had come out. I
believe it was out of a university in
Germany. and they had looked at
different personas and they were
presenting these personas to AI
um talking about what kind of salary
should I look at, should I ask for?
And it was some kind of a medical
specialist uh
position,
right? And if AI thought it was a man,
it told them that they should ask for a
starting salary of $400,000.
If AI thought it was a woman, it said
that they should ask for a starting
salary of $280,000.
That's a huge that's a huge difference.
So,
absolutely is. I have had I have heard
the argument well it it is it it's not
up up to us you know to uh to be able to
monitor that but if we do not monitor
unfair bias that is out in the world
all we're doing is perpetuating that so
we so it is it is the type of thing
where we need to be aware of it
and I think we need to take action on
that so we don't perpetuate those bad
things. I mean, I'm data quality, right?
Data quality is all about the data is
right. You can trust it. Real
reflection, right,
of of of what we need. And
the whole reason we care about it is
because [clears throat] we can trust it
and use it with confidence,
right? you know, and that that brings up
something really important. You know,
when you're talking about facts, you
know, there's clearly been disparities
in pay um and they're documented, you
know, so if all you if you've got the
the the larger portion of your data set
is based on things that um
hopefully have changed and and been
changed by, you know, by intention and
sometimes by policy.
These are things that you your models
have to be adjusted for. It's it's not a
bias from uh even someone's opinion.
It's just that historically things have
been a certain way and you have to
understand when you're asking these
these models to give you back
information or recommendations, it can
only make them based on what it knows,
not on what what it doesn't know. So if
it's not educated enough to understand
policy changes, either from a regulatory
standpoint or even inside of a company,
it's going to give you bad
recommendations.
Yes. And I would rather see AI come back
and say historically this is what we see
right
and instead of um
telling you ask this do this I would
really rather have it come back and say
his like I said historically something
looks a a certain a certain way
right
instead of stating it as fact that this
is what we should do now.
Yeah, that's that is a really important
thing. Now, it kind of gets to another
topic. Um just this whole our whole
conversation can be, you know, framed in
so many different ways because there's
so many threads that all go back to, you
know, the the pace that we're we're
moving. Uh we need to slow down and and
and take a take a hard look at what
we're doing, how we're doing it, and why
we're doing it. And what is it that
we're trying to accomplish? M, you know,
you just touched on this, the illusion
of intelligence. Essentially, AI systems
are confident. They're coherent and
wrong all at the same time. How does bad
data hide behind good output?
Yeah. Yeah. And and
taking the time. Now, I I am going to
push back a little bit about a comment
that you just made about
um having to slow down. I truly believe
that people need to understand that
doing things right the first time may
feel like it's slowing down,
right?
But what is the cost when thing when you
ignore those basic things that you think
take too long at the beginning,
but then it ends up completely
sabotaging the whole project,
right? or you have to do the rework or
then you do all the things that you
should have done first after some time
period much much more expensive. So yes,
the illusion of going slow.
Mhm.
But sometimes that illusion of going
slower actually helps us go faster and
in the long run actually saves us money.
So I think that's a really and I have
seen it again and again over my career
different new you know the big silver
bullet technology comes into place
right
people are anxious to put that in and it
always comes back let's get the data
let's get the data right
and
slow down to go fast
that's very very well said I couldn't
Couldn't agree more. I I know it's it's
not fun work sometimes. You know, people
don't get excited uh necessarily to go
and clean up the data, get it fit for
use, data wrangling, whatever you want
to call it. But sadly, more people that
are that are in roles where they're they
have a title of analyst in there
somewhere, they're they've spent far
more time wrangling data, getting it fit
for use than they have actually doing
the analysis that it was intended to
enable.
Yes. Yeah. We've def we have definitely
seen seen that over time. The good news
is there are people like me who actually
get excited about data
excited about data quality. So I've had
intersections in my career where I could
have gone different places. I always
came back to data. Always came back to
data quality because I understand how
important it is. So, I know that there
are other people that are out there that
are like that. And I'm going to tie this
in just a little bit to the leadership
uh point that you made earlier.
Um, we need to not only clean up the
data, we need to prevent the problems
from happening. So yeah, there may be
some cleanup that we have to do,
but from a leadership point of view, we
need leaders to understand look at root
cause, look at prevention.
Prevention is always cheaper than than
um than the cleanup. Is that difference
between fire prevention and fire
[clears throat] fighting? Is it better
to stop a forest fire
or to fight a fire once it starts? I
think that makes it really easy to see
the difference between just prevention
and correction. We have to have some of
both,
but too often leadership focuses only on
the correction piece. We need equal
focus on that prevention
and getting to root causes. you you said
that ethics starts in the metadata. Can
you unpack that a little bit?
So, so metadata
um data about data. So, before some
people's eyes glaze over, so metadata is
the basic things that you need to know
about your data,
right?
What is the name of the field called
where the data is stored? What is the
definition? Are there lists of allowed
values if it's some kind of an ID or a
code for instance?
So metadata the basic things that you
need to know about your data. So if we
do not have those common definitions and
it really comes down to like this common
language and understanding about the
data itself, we're going to have a
really hard time
using it in the right places and
understanding the output of the things
that that come to us. And so so anything
that shows bias,
we don't want to have that reflected in
the metadata. Everything, you know, that
foundation
um builds up from that,
right? Yeah, that's it's an interesting
area just because there's
all too often, you know, there's not a
coordinated
data and analytics inside of some
organizations. one group's doing
something one way, one's doing it the
other, and they're if their language and
terminology they're using is not the
same. It can get really confusing. It
can I mean, it's a I don't even know how
many times that I've stumbled into
things like that where I'm like, "Oh my
gosh, you guys are measuring the same
thing, but it's different. You're
looking at it through a different lens.
Is there a great reason for that?" Maybe
there is, but some sometimes there's
just not. they just haven't talked and
actually had these kind of uh exercises.
Yeah. And and that's where the
governance piece comes in
because if you have good data governance
to me what that means is you are
bringing people together,
right?
They may ne have never met each other
but they're all using the same data.
They may call it something different.
They may depend on each other in a way
that they haven't before. Good
governance will bring those people
together and facilitate the
conversations and those kinds of
decisions and things have just grown up.
They they call things different because
we used to have a platform that only
looked at sales. We used to have a
platform that only looked at the
products. We used to have a platform
that only looked at the marketing. We
now have you know all kinds of platforms
that bring these these various areas
together. That is where you really see
the data quality problems and you really
see the differences in how people have
been using looking at managing
treating the data which makes governance
very very important for that reason to
bring those um disperate people
together.
I love how you're describing it because
far too often people think of governance
as controls. Um, and to some extent it
can be, but it's really more about
enabling people uh to really produce
results that you can trust and it's
there as a protection. But I'm sure
you've heard leaders say things like,
uh, we'll clean it up later. Uh, what's
your response when you hear that?
[laughter]
Yeah. Oh, I love this one. So, let let's
take an example of some kind of
integrated platform like ERP, enterprise
resource planning. It will have things
like your finance and your manufacturing
and your sales and, you know, bringing
all these systems together into one
platform. You literally spend tens of
millions of dollars in in getting the
technology and being able to migrate and
integrate that data as it comes. And at
the last minute, well, it's we just not
even at the last minute. At some point
along the way, they're saying, you know,
yes, let's just load it. We'll clean it
up later. Okay. A few fallacies in that
thinking. Number one is you really think
you can load it
if it is not if it has not been put into
the state it needs to go into the
technology.
So you're going to have a lot of data
that absolutely can't lo cannot load.
The second one is once you get it in
there do you think that you're actually
ready to go to production? Do you think
people can actually use that data? So I
do have experience
um in seeing the difference between
those who took care of the data. This
was the same large global migration,
right?
That I'm not going to give you any more
information about large global
migration.
all of the sites around the world who
bought into the data quality message
that we were bringing forward uh the
things that they needed to do to to look
at the quality of the data. Say this is
what it looks like today in our system.
This is what it needs to look like
tomorrow in the new system. What is the
gap?
Right?
How do we change that? Every site that
did that around the world was able to um
close their financial books. Like
quarter end was something like two weeks
after uh month end was two weeks after
this huge migration.
Quarter end close was six weeks. I mean
absolutely able to close all of their
books. They were able to ship products.
The only site where they refused to do
any of the data quality work was the
only site who could not ship product.
And I know because I was on the desk who
had to call people in the middle of the
night
around the world and say we have an
emergency and we have something we have
to take care of here. So I have seen it
and I have lived it. So that that is
that that is a common a common thing
that really doesn't work.
Yeah, those that example is u I think
pretty compelling if people are not sure
whether they should really do this
exercise or not. [laughter]
I want to talk about another thing. I
mean it's interesting because you and I
have used some some similar terminology
but you know from a different lens. So
I've talked about technical debt
recently and I've talked about data
technical debt, but you are talking
about something that is data quality
debt. What does that debt look like and
who ends up paying it?
Well, I I think maybe my words around
data quality might be similar to the
data debt. So people might be more
familiar with technical debt which is
the idea there are certain things when
we're putting in a new system and maybe
we need to customize some things or we
need to change some processes or we need
to train people like whatever that is
right
and they decide oh we don't have time to
do that. Well, you know, there is an
approach there that tracks that and they
understand that if they skip doing that,
they have incurred some technical debt
which will need to be paid at some point
in time,
right?
It is the very same thing around the
data and the data quality. Oh, we need
to
uh analyze and assess and profile our
data to see what is that big gap between
what it looks like today and what it
needs to look like tomorrow. There are
certain things that we need to do to
close that gap. If we choose not to do
that, we have incurred that data or data
quality debt. Just in the same way that
technical debt is incurred, there will
be a cost
to not taking care of it now, there will
be a bigger cost to taking care of it
later. I mean, you know, I told my kids
this all the time and it applies to
everything in life. Pay now or pay
later. But if you pay later, you always
pay more.
So going along with that debt if I can
give you an example. So there is there
is something called the Rule of Tens.
This was something that was identified a
long time ago. Um according to when you
are doing a a implementation. So let's
say that you have requirements, you have
design, you have you know your coding,
you go live, you have uh being in
production. Okay, if you find a problem
and this applied to software but it also
exactly applies to data that we've seen
this over the years. If you find the
data problem in the requirements in the
design stage, you know, each one
exponentially,
if it cost you a dollar to fix it early
on, the next stage it'll cost you $10.
If you don't do anything about it until
testing, you're probably at $1,000.
So, that is an example of the kind of
debt you incur. And in fact, I was I did
a presentation, a workshop last week in
Phoenix at DMA Data Management
Association. They have a a chapter there
in Phoenix. And I was talking about the
Rule of Tens. There's a gentleman who
raises his hand and he says it's not the
Rule of Tens, it's thousands. He says
because when you get into production and
then you have you you like you business
cannot carry forward. He says it's
thousands and thousands.
So that that is just this example of the
progression
of the debt
and how much more expensive it is when
it is delayed.
Yeah. Th this is this is a really really
powerful thing to to really think about
because I don't think people necessarily
are are doing the doing the the math
properly to really calculate the cost of
inaction. U it's a it's a big big deal
and it snowballs just like we were
talking about training the AI models.
You know you're you're training it to
make things worse by not addressing the
data quality. That's what you're
building. You're instantiating it into
your organizational structure and you're
setting yourself up for a really really
bad outcome. Um I'm I'm certainly not
going to be a person that would
challenge you when you come in and tell
me we got to fix the data for that
reason.
Well, okay. So, here's the thing. Some
people, they may say, "Oh, data quality.
Oh, it's just correcting the data." Or,
"Who cares about this?" And it's like,
right,
you can see I'm pretty enthusiastic
about data quality. I have been for all
these years, right?
But I never do data quality for the sake
of data quality. Why do we do data
quality? For the sake of whatever you as
an organization is trying to accomplish.
I don't care if you're forprofit in any
vertical. Government, education, healthc
care,
we only do data quality because it helps
our organizations do the things that
they need to do. Right.
That's that's why it's there. It's not
there to get in your way. It's there to
help you do whatever your organization
cares about. We we can help you do it
better.
Right. So, as we're kind of, you know,
winding down a little bit, maybe can
take this a little bit further and maybe
talk about some practical steps
organizations should be taking to make
sure that quality is part of the AI life
cycle. It's not a gatekeeping function.
Okay. Yes. So, thank you for me for
bringing that up because I do have a
methodology that I have developed over
the years is called 10 steps to quality
data and trusted information. I
definitely I call myself a second
generation pioneer because I learned
from the three gentlemen that in the US
I call the first generation pioneers in
the late 80s and early 90s who were
really bringing visibility to data
quality as an issue as skills thing
things that you need to learn. So I call
myself a second generation pioneer
because I learned directly from all of
them.
Tom Redmond, Larry English and Rich
Wang. um out of MIT
and my innovation and building on the
shoulders of those giants was my 10
steps methodology. It is well if you
don't care ah here's the book executing
data quality projects. The subtitle is
the name of the methodology. So there's
a second edition that is out where I can
feel very confident and comfortable that
if you need to know how to deal with
data quality, how to create, how to
manage, how to sustain the quality of
data, this is a methodology that
provides you a roadmap flexible,
scalable, I mean one person, four-week
project, many people, many months
project and It has proven itself.
It uh different languages use it. It is
available in Chinese, Japanese. The
Spanish translation is underway. But I
mean people around the world, different
cultures, different types of
organizations, big uses, small uses. So
to me this is really the practical how
do we go about dealing with this data
quality problem that you and I have just
been discussing
right
and the good thing about this it is very
complementaryary to other resources but
it is the road map in the middle of the
what do we do and the really good
detailed books and resources that go
into a lot of detail about a slice of
the data quality pie. This is what keeps
you from getting lost in all the detail.
Where are we?
What do we need to do? And you bring in
this other information. It complements
the other things that are out there. So
learning and training your people in how
to address data quality is a really
really important
leadership decision
because is it is the leaders in an
organization who say I understand why
data quality is important to what we
care about in whatever my organization
is. I want people to be trained in how
to do that and I am willing to make that
um an important part of our funding and
our investment decisions. So the 10 mill
tens of millions of dollars we're
spending on technology will actually
work for us.
Right. That that's that is
really amazing to me when you're you're
you're telling me that how far this has
gone is you know you're having a global
impact on data quality. That is really
amazing. I mean I can't I can't even
explain to you how much I I admire that
because it's not a it's not an area that
is um sometimes it's not an area that's
even wellreceived because it it exposes
some things that people um can be
embarrassed about. Like I remember doing
some data profiling at different times
and there were assumptions made about
the values that you might find in a
particular field and you do the profile
and you find out oh my gosh no one has
really maintained this at all. It's it's
terrible.
So it's a really important thing.
It it is really important and it is
natural for people to feel somewhat
defensive and not want to uncover the
problems. But I learned early on in my
career, there was one of the first data
quality projects that I had done as an
employee,
which is where I got my feet wet in
global high-tech companies,
right?
And we found some problems that were
completely unexpected
and costing the company tens of millions
of dollars.
And the person who had sponsored this
project was also the owner of this
system
right
for many years. It would have been
really easy for that woman to say or it
could have been a man. It doesn't
matter. But it happened to be the owner
of the system was a woman. It could have
been e would have been easy for her to
say, you know what, we didn't expect
that. Let's just put this under the
covers. We're could nothing to see here.
Everybody go home.
Right. I loved the fact and learned from
her that she stepped up and she she
shared the problems widely and she said
if we don't talk about the problems
nothing will get changed. So she took a
risk. She showed some courage.
Yes.
And and stepped up. And to me that's
what a real leader does and I've tried
to emulate that and I learned from that.
Fortunately, I had that good example
when we were talking about quality and
the the need to really build this into
the culture of an organization and when
you're thinking about how in important
it is when you're building AI solutions
that the stuff actually is addressed
kind of in in the process, not after the
fact. um how do you think about you know
operationalizing that and what do
leaders really need to be doing to
ensure that they're they're approaching
this properly and and it's getting uh
getting into the DNA of the company.
Yeah. So so the the 10 steps are
starting with the business needs. they
will go all the way to a step nine which
is really a handoff toward
operationalizing the things that you
found as you were addressing the initial
data quality problems an important piece
there's a couple of important pieces
there one of them is how do we even know
that it's worthwhile for us to do that
and I have a step around business impact
techniques that can help you be able to
in a qualitative ative and a
quantitative way be able to show the
value of looking at your data quality.
You don't have to just take my word for
it. I have some ways that you can
actually look at that and apply that to
your company. The other piece is in
order to operationalize something,
people have to carry it out. People have
to be willing to make that change,
right? So um within the methodology
there's a step 10 that visually
communicate manage and engage with
people throughout. We have to deal with
the human element
right
of our data quality work. Everything we
do around data quality triggers some
kind of a change.
Oh wow. We need to train someone that's
a change. We need to refine a role. We
need to refine or create new processes.
we find a technology bug like all of
those things have to work together for
the data to work. What is that
triggering change? So, it's really
important for leadership to understand
that human element and to be able to
support the things that need to happen
in order for people to be willing to
work through the change, embrace the
change, and be able to see that value.
and people will
and then they will get excited and then
that will carry on. But to your point of
operationalizing
that is an important piece of making
that ultimately work and sustain
the things that we're trying to do.
Yeah. And I I I think the the importance
from a cultural perspective um of making
it a a safe environment for people to to
identify these things and just just own
it. It it's, you know, my my parents
always taught me when I was young, um,
if if you do something that that that
you shouldn't do, um, or you've broken
something or whatever, don't let us
discover it. You tell us. And you know
that was a it was a different way of
thinking. But you know that that
actually did set me up to have uh a much
easier transition into the working world
because I understood that I kind of had
to own things that that I was
responsible for.
Yes. And and that that is such a good
example. You and I had parents who
taught us the same type of thing.
[laughter] It's it's also helpful for
people to think about the fact that
they may own something that they didn't
create the problems for,
right?
And these systems grow up in organic
ways and sometimes not in good ways. So
I really try to focus on the fact that
processes have changed, the world
outside of us have changed, requirements
have changed. I'm really not into
pointing fingers at the people that were
involved with it. We are really just
trying to make this better. And and
to that kind of attitude goes back to
what you were saying about creating that
safe
Yes. environment where people can talk
about the problems and come up with the
solutions and and not and and not feel
like they're taking a huge risk because
it is safe to do that.
So that was the perfect word.
Yeah, it's always wise to have the
people closest to the action be part of
the solution. It just it it just it
saves a lot of hassle. And honestly, the
more people see that that's an
acceptable thing to identify a problem
and actually work on it collectively to
fix it, the the better off you are
because people will feel safe and
they'll they'll understand this is not
lip service. You know, that leadership
really does want us to be comfortable
and they understand we're human beings.
Absolutely.
That that's powerful. you know, people
really need need they need to understand
that leadership is uh sometimes
difficult and that you actually have to
own something that you'd rather not have
to own. But that's a really important
characteristic in a leader. So, I mean,
thank thank you for sharing that. Um it
it occurred to me as as we're
we're we're talking about, you know, the
the need for this kind of training that
there may be some folks out there
listening that they may they may need
your services, you know, at Granite
Falls Consulting. So, I would I'd love
to to have you just tell us how people
can get in touch with you. Um, and where
can they find your your book and you
know, certainly in the show notes of
later, I'll make sure that all that
stuff is available, but if you if you
wouldn't mind just telling telling folks
where to how to reach you.
Yes. Uh, so my company is Granite Falls
Consulting. Um, Gfalls.com.
So, G for Granite Falls as in
waterfalls. G F A Ls as in sam.com. So
you can find me out there,
datgfalls.com.
Um, connect with me on LinkedIn, send me
an email and we can have a conversation
about what it is you need and how I I
can help you uh be able to bring
forward. I do the consulting, I do the
training and do the one-on-one coaching
and mentoring if if that is helpful for
people also. So, those are kind of the
three main areas, but all around the
data quality and governance piece that
will help your organization.
Well, thank you so much for that. I I I
can't can't tell you that I've run
across a whole bunch of people that are
as enthusiastic and actually enjoy the
work like you do. And uh I I I think
that's a a real um uh valuable asset
that organizations should be thinking
about taking advantage of. Maybe you can
uh get your own teams uh energized just
bringing in a good coach and taking some
instruction. Um, this is such an
important area particularly as we're
we're heading into this crazy
transformation with AI and things are
being more instantiated all the time in
in in the foundations of of this
technology. It we can't afford not to
deal with the data quality. So, thank
you for that and thank you so much for
taking the time to to sit with me. This
has been a fun conversation for me. Uh,
and I hope our our listeners will have
enjoyed will enjoy this as well and I
hope it's been it's fun for you. So,
thank you so much for that.
Yeah, absolutely. Thanks, Chris. It's
just been a pleasure. Love talking with
you.
Well, folks, that's it for this episode
of the Signal Room. If today's
conversation sparked something in you,
an idea, a challenge, a perspective
worth amplifying. I'd love to hear from
you. Message me on LinkedIn or visit
signalaroompodcast.com
to explore being a guest on an upcoming
episode. I'd love to have you. We're
here to amplify the signals that matter
across leadership, ethics, and
innovation. Until next time, stay tuned,
stay curious, and stay human. That's it
for this episode of The Signal Room. If
today's conversation sparked something
in you, an idea, a challenge, or a
perspective worth amplifying, I'd love
to hear from you. Message me on LinkedIn
or visit signalaroompodcast.com
to explore being a guest on an upcoming
episode. Until next time, stay tuned,
stay curious, and stay human.